Guide to the Miles Wilson Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
Miles Wilson Accessions
1965-2016
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Wilson, Miles
UPWC.16130
8 Linear Feet
8 boxes
Multiple accessions from Texas State University professor and writer, Miles Wilson. Materials include research and drafts for his books, Line of Fall, Fire Season, Going the Distance, and Harm: Poems.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Miles Wilson, 2016, 2018
Biographical Note
Miles Wilson was the founding director of the MFA program in creative writing at Texas State University, where he is Distinguished Professor Emeritus. He is the author of three prize-winning books: Fire Season (2014), Harm (2003), and Line of Fall (1989.) His newest book, Woodswork: New and Selected Stories of the American West, is forthcoming in 2018 from the University of New Mexico Press.
Wilson served three fire seasons (1964, 1965, 1967) as a member of the Dalton Hotshots, a U.S. Forest Service Interregional Fire Crew based on the Angeles National Forest in California. While serving with the Dalton Hotshots, Wilson received a Bachelors degree in English at Pomona College and a Masters of Fine Arts in Creative Writing at the University of Oregon.
He is the recipient of numerous awards for his previous publications, including the John Simmons Short Fiction Award from the University of Iowa Press for Line of Fall and the Violet Crown Book Award from the Writer's League of Texas/Barnes & Noble for Harm. He has held fellowships from the National Endowment for the Arts and the Christopher Isherwood Foundation. Wilson currently divides his time between San Marcos, Texas and his native Oregon.
Scope and Contents
Multiple accessions from Texas State University professor and writer, Miles Wilson. Materials include research and drafts for his books, Line of Fall, Fire Season, Going the Distance, and Harm: Poems.
Index Terms
Subjects
Poetry; Authors
Subjects (Corporations)
The Wittliff Collections; Texas State University
- Accession 2016-130
  Abstract
  Archival materials following the career of Texas State University professor and writer, Miles Wilson from 1966-2016. Majority of the materials in the collection are manuscript drafts for Line of Fall and Fire Season. Included are book catalogs; royalties for the drafts; and characters analyses and synopsis for Fire Season. Some of the materials within the collection are in poor condition because they were charred in a fire. The folder titles preceding a semicolon reflect Wilson's original descriptions.
  - "Line of Fall: Iowa"; Correspondence on Line of Fall (2 folders), 1989-2006 (Box 2486, Folder 1-2)
  - "Royalties: Miles Wilson"; Royalties that Wilson received throughout the years, 1996-2013 (Box 2486, Folder 3)
  - University of Iowa Press book catalogs, 1989-2004 (Box 2486, Folder 4)
  - University of Iowa Press book catalogs, 1987-2000 (Box 2486, Folder 5)
  - "Everything"; Annotated "Everything" manuscript draft (Box 2486, Folder 6)
  - "Gospel Hump"; Annotated "Gospel Hump" draft and notes (Box 2486, Folder 7)
  - "The Lord of Misrule at Separation Creek"; Annotated manuscript drafts (Box 2486, Folder 8)
  - "On Tour with Max"; Annotated manuscript drafts, including The Dallas Morning News article about "On Tour with Max", 1995-2009 (Box 2486, Folder 9)
  - "Outrider"; Annotated manuscript drafts and notes (Box 2486, Folder 10)
  - "Toliver"; Annotated manuscript drafts and notes (Box 2486, Folder 11)
  - "Wyoming"; Annotated drafts (Box 2486, Folder 12)
  - "Going Away"; Annotated manuscript drafts and notes (Box 2486, Folder 13)
  - "Figuring the Quiet"; Annotated manuscript drafts, Fall 1965 (Box 2486, Folder 14)
  - "Long Green"; Annotated manuscript drafts and notes (Box 2486, Folder 15)
  - "Baja"; Annotated "Baja" manuscript drafts and notes, 1966 (Box 2486, Folder 16)
  - Fire Season, 1966-2014
    - Part 1, pages 1-78, 1966-1976 (Box 2486, Folder 17)
    - Part 2, pages 79-133, 1966-1976 (Box 2486, Folder 18)
    - Part 3, pages 134-213, 1966-1976 (Box 2486, Folder 19)
    - Part 4, pages 214-266, 1966-1976 (Box 2486, Folder 20)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 1-132 (1 of 2) (Box 2486, Folder 21)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 133-244 (2 of 2) (Box 2486, Folder 22)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 1-137 (1 of 2) (Box 2487, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 138-267 (2 of 2) (Box 2487, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 1-127 (1 of 2) (Box 2487, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript draft, pages 128-239 (2 of 2) (Box 2487, Folder 4)
    - Bound manuscript, undated (Box 2487, Folder 5)
    - Bound copy, 2014 (Box 2487, Folder 6)
    - "AWP Entries & Synopsis"; Themes and synopsis for Fire Season, including a letter from Associated Writing Program, 1985 (Box 2487, Folder 7)
    - "Fire Season Hand Notes"; Notes on Fire Season (Box 2487, Folder 8)
    - Title page and pg. 266 of Fire Season (Box 2487, Folder 9)
    - "Fire Season Drafts, 1971-."; Annotated manuscript draft, 1985 (Box 2487, Folder 10-11)
    - Unknown burned manuscript drafts (Box 2487, Folder 12)
    - "2006 Year Sier: drafts, notes, letters, reads"; Correspondence, notes, and annotated manuscript drafts of Fire Season, 1982-1994 (Box 2487, Folder 13)
    - "Fire Season: SFA Press/ Contests/ Cover"; Fire Season cover, reviews, and correspondence, 2012-2014 (Box 2487, Folder 14)
    - "Agents/Editors-Fire Season"; Correspondence from Random House, Atlantic Monthly Press, and others, 1981-2007 (Box 2487, Folder 15)
    - "Hepworth/Conference/Fire Season"; Correspondence and book catalogs, 1987-1993 (Box 2487, Folder 16)
    - "Utah-Fire Season"; Correspondence between Wilson and University of Utah Press, and Request for Proposal, 1989-2008 (Box 2487, Folder 17)
    - "SMV-Fire Season"; Correspondence and reviews on Fire Season, 1991 (Box 2487, Folder 18)
    - "Novel Synopsis"; Fire Season synopsis (Box 2487, Folder 19)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Fire Season, including notes, pages 1-171 (Box 2487, Folder 20)
    - "Fire Season/ [?] Rev./ 150 pp"; Annotated Fire Season manuscript draft, 1994 (Box 2488, Folder 1)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Fire Season, pages 1-273, 1994 (Box 2488, Folder 2)
    - Annotated Fire Season draft, including synopsis (2 folders), 1976 (Box 2488, Folder 3-4)
    - Annotated Fire Season manuscript draft (2 folders), 1976 (Box 2488, Folder 5-6)
    - Fire Season manuscript draft (3 folders), undated (Box 2488, Folder 7-9)
    - Synopsis, themes, and character analysis for Fire Season (Box 2488, Folder 10)
    - Annotated First Draft of Fire Season, undated (Box 2488, Folder 11)
    - Annotated Fire Season draft, including letter to "Kim" about corrections for the book, 2014 (Box 2488, Folder 12)
    - 2nd PDF from Stephen F. Austin Press (SFA) of Fire Season, December 13, 2013 (Box 2488, Folder 13)
    - Annotated Fire Season draft, including notes on the novel, and Miles Wilson Document Summary, 2013 (Box 2488, Folder 14)
  - Line of Fall, 1977-1989
    - Manuscript draft of Line of Fall, edited by Kathy Lewis, May 5, 1989 (Box 2488, Folder 15)
    - The Line of Fall page proofs, including correspondence between Wilson and Kathy Lewis, 1989 (Box 2488, Folder 16)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Line of Fall, 1989 (Box 2489, Folder 1)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Line of Fall, pages 1-234, undated (Box 2489, Folder 2)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Line of Fall, pages 1-234, 1989 (Box 2489, Folder 3)
    - Annotated Line of Fall: A Collection of Short Stories draft, pages 1-204, 1977-1987 (Box 2489, Folder 4)
    - Annotated manuscript draft of Line of Fall, pages 1-178, 1989 (Box 2489, Folder 5)
  - Three copies of posters for Miles Wilson Reading Event, March 17, 1988 (Box 2489, Folder 6)
- Accession 2018-061
  Archival materials from author Miles Wilson dating 1965-2016. Material includes correspondence pertaining to the acquisition of the J. Frank Dobie papers by William Wittliff and the inception of the Southwest Writers Collection at Southwest Texas State University (Texas State University) San Marcos, Texas, as well as annotated drafts of early poetry and short prose; submissions to various poetry and short story anthologies; rejection slips and editor correspondence. The bulk of the material includes drafts of poems eventually included in the anthology Harm: Poems and early manuscript drafts of Going the Distance and Fire Season. Included are correspondence, royalty statements, reviews, marketing materials and annotated manuscripts for Harm and Fire Season. The folder titles preceding a semicolon reflect Wilson's original descriptions.
  - "Wittliff: Dobie-Southwest Collection"; Correspondence, newspaper articles, newsletters and notes on the inception and opening of the Wittliff Southwestern Writers Collection (2 folders), 1986-1994 (Box 2778, Folder 1-2)
  - "Hearon, Bird, Harrigan-SW Writers Dedication"; TKL writers event memorandums, author stipends, payment vouchers. Includes correspondence with Stephen Harrigan, Sarah Bird and Shelby Hearon, 1986, 1991 (Box 2778, Folder 3)
  - "TKL-Holland $"; TKL funding of Dick Holland salary and R.G. Vliet estate, 1993 (Box 2778, Folder 4)
  - "Ann Vliet-R.G. Vliet"; Notes on appraisal value of Vliet collection (Box 2778, Folder 5)
  - "Baird Ranch"; Correspondence pertaining to the Baird Ranch endowment and the creation of the Southwest Studies program, 1989 (Box 2778, Folder 6)
  - "Task Force: SW Writers Collection and Center"; Correspondence, news clippings, newsletters and proposals pertaining to The Center for the Study of the Southwest, Southwest Texas State, 1989-1992 (Box 2778, Folder 7)
  - "The Near Coast of Darkness/Thesis"; Annotated manuscripts of "The Near Coast of Darkness", 1966 (Box 2778, Folder 8)
  - "Apology for Being Your Husband"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 9)
  - "Donna at Bagby"; Annotated drafts of "Donna at Bagby" (Box 2778, Folder 10)
  - "Blood-You a Week from Wednesday"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 11)
  - "Proposal to My Wife"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 12)
  - "Report to the Founding Fathers"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 13)
  - "Denver Girls"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 14)
  - "Snow Driving"; Annotated drafts and unedited copies of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 15)
  - "For Fifteen Dollars"; Annotated draft of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 16)
  - "George the Dog"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 17)
  - "Oath at Caliber Creek"; Annotated drafts and typescript copies of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 18)
  - "She Was a Good Woman"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 19)
  - "Turtz in the Provinces"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 20)
  - "Union Scale"; Annotated draft of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 21)
  - "A Vision of Green"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 22)
  - "A Wheat God Dying Young"; Annotated drafts and unedited copy of poem (Box 2778, Folder 23)
  - "After the Blizzard"; Annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 24)
  - "Baja"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of the poem (Box 2778, Folder 25)
  - "Believing in Texas"; Typescript copy and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 26)
  - "Blossom Bar, Pistol River"; Annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 27)
  - "Body"; Typescript copy and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 28)
  - "Body Song"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 29)
  - "Claire (Kate) If You Come"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 30)
  - "Fathers"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 31)
  - "For San Dwayne Francisco"; Typescript copies, annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 32)
  - "A Geography of the John Day River"; Critique of Wilson poems, typescript copies and annotated drafts of the poem "A Geography of the John Day River", 2007, undated (Box 2778, Folder 33)
  - "Provisions (Getting There)"; Typescript copy and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 34)
  - "Harney County/High Desert/Dying in Oregon-See Blossom Bar"; Typescript copies and annotated Drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 35)
  - "Horsepasture Mountain Lookout"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 36)
  - "Husband in the Garden"; Typescript copy of poem (Box 2778, Folder 37)
  - "In Hand"; Typescript copies and annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 38)
  - "Into It"; Annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 39)
  - "Joe, Dead"; Annotated, handwritten draft of poem (Box 2778, Folder 40)
  - "Keeping Track"; Typescript copy of poem (Box 2778, Folder 41)
  - "Last Spring"; Typescript copy of poem (Box 2778, Folder 42)
  - "Life and Death"; Typescript, annotated copies of poem (Box 2778, Folder 43)
  - "Light and Dark at Meacham Pass"; Typescript and handwritten annotated drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 44)
  - "Night Beach Snake"; Annotated typescript draft and typescript copy (Box 2778, Folder 45)
  - "Nights in Crosley" Annotated typescript draft of poem, photocopy of handwritten draft (Box 2778, Folder 46)
  - "Notes from the End of a Five-Year Marriage"; Typescript copy of poem annotated typescript drafts (Box 2778, Folder 47)
  - "Out Of"; Annotate holograph and typescript drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 48)
  - "The Promise Keepers"; Annotated holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 49)
  - "Provisions"; Annotated typescript drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 50)
  - "Rider"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 51)
  - "The Rising"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 52)
  - "Sanctuaries"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 53)
  - "Short Season in the North Cascades"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript drafts of poem, letter to "the editor" (Box 2778, Folder 54)
  - "Stripper"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 55)
  - "Taking Stock"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 56)
  - "Terminal/Evidence"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 57)
  - "These Days"; Typescript copy and annotated holograph draft of poem (Box 2778, Folder 58)
  - "Things to Know in Wedderburn"; Typescript copy and annotated typescript drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 59)
  - "The View from Frissel Point"; Typescript copy, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 60)
  - "Vita"; Typescript copy and annotated typescript drafts of the poem "The Vita", typescript annotated drafts of the poems "Apology for Death" and "One Against Death" (Box 2778, Folder 61)
  - "Whitehorse Rim"; Typescript copies and annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 62)
  - "The Will to Fail"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 63)
  - "You, Theodore Roethke"; Typescript copies, annotated typescript and holograph drafts of poem (Box 2778, Folder 64)
  - "High School/College Journal/Notes"; annotated typescript short prose, journal entries (Box 2779, Folder 1)
  - Annotated typescript drafts of "The Rising (Box 2779, Folder 2)
  - Poems, annotated typescript drafts of "The Last Full Measure" (Box 2779, Folder 3)
  - "From the Kansas City Terminal"; Annotated, typescript draft (Box 2779, Folder 4)
  - "The Sound of Laughter"; Annotated typescript draft (Box 2779, Folder 5)
  - "Suppose a Wind"; Annotated typescript drafts (Box 2779, Folder 6)
  - "Poems-Juvenilia"; Annotated typescript drafts of titled and untitled poems (Box 2779, Folder 7)
  - "Prose-Juvenilia"; Annotated typescript drafts of short stories, 1965 (Box 2779, Folder 8)
  - "Texas Tech Poetry Ass."; Texas Tech University Press correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 2779, Folder 9)
  - "Naomi Nye-Texas Obs Poems"; Correspondence with Naomi Nye of The Texas Observer, annotated typescript draft of "Believing in Texas, 1995-1996 (Box 2779, Folder 10)
  - "Scott Slovic/Isle Poems"; Correspondence with Scott Slovic, University of Nevada, Reno, 1995 (Box 2779, Folder 11)
  - "Ahsahta/Illinois Poetry Mss."; Poetry manuscripts and correspondence submitted to Ahsahta Press and the University of Missouri press, rejection letters, notes, 1982-1991 (Box 2779, Folder 12)
  - Harm, 1982-2010
    - "Saner/Harm"; Correspondence with Reg Saner, 2002, undated (Box 2779, Folder 13)
    - Letter to John Nichols requesting manuscript review of Harm, 1994 (Box 2779, Folder 14)
    - "Rick Bass-Harm"; Correspondence and notes, 2001-2002 (Box 2779, Folder 15)
    - "Scott Slovic-Harm"; Correspondence between Wilson and Slovic, 2002 (Box 2779, Folder 16)
    - "Royalty Statements Harm"; Royalty statements for Harm, 2004-2013 (Box 2779, Folder 17)
    - "Harm-Reader Reports/Editorial Board My Responses"; Reader reports, editorial board meeting, correspondence and notes University of Nevada Press, 1998-2000 (Box 2779, Folder 18)
    - "Harm – Reviews & Ads"; Reviews and ads for Harm, correspondence with the University of Nevada Press, 2003-2010 (Box 2779, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence concerning Harm, University of Nevada Press release, cover photo, 2003-2004 (Box 2779, Folder 20)
    - "Chris Campbell/Marketing/Author's Questionnaire"; Marketing, author's questionnaire, book endorsements, correspondence pertaining to the publication of Harm, 2002-2003 (Box 2779, Folder 21)
    - "Harm/Nevada/Campbell/House et/emails"; CD, correspondence pertaining Harm marketing, awards, cover design University of Nevada press, 2002-2004 (Box 2779, Folder 22)
    - "Nevada-Harm"; Correspondence pertaining to Harm, public contract, 1998-2002 (Box 2779, Folder 23)
    - Harm University of Nevada Press correspondence, original and copyedited manuscript, 2000, 2003 (Box 2779, Folder 24)
    - "Harm: Corrected Page Proofs"; Correspondence and corrected page proofs for Harm, 2000 (Box 2779, Folder 25)
    - "Harm"; Author annotated manuscript drafts of Harm, correspondence with the University of Nevada Press, 2001 (Box 2779, Folder 26)
    - "M. Dalrymple: Emails and Copyedited mss."; Correspondence with Margaret Dalrymple pertaining to Harm, copyedited manuscript, 2002 (Box 2779, Folder 27)
    - Holograph notes on Harm with page numbers and sections (Box 2779, Folder 28)
  - Going the Distance, undated
    - "6"; Going the Distance manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 28)
    - "5"; Going the Distance annotated manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 29)
    - "4"; Going the Distance manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 30)
    - "3"; Going the Distance manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 31)
    - "2"; Going the Distance annotated manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 32)
    - "Miles Wilson Excerpts from Going the Distance 1"; manuscript (Box 2779, Folder 33)
    - "Earliest Version of Harm (Bone)"; Bone manuscript, rejection letter from Yale University Press (Box 2779, Folder 34)
  - "Texas Short Stories II-Body"; Correspondence pertaining to the submission and acceptance of "Body", 1998-1999 (Box 2780, Folder 1)
  - "Best Texas Writing 2-1998/99"; Correspondence regarding the of the submission of "Why God Must Permit Everything", 1998-1999 (Box 2780, Folder 2)
  - "Baseball Anthology"; Correspondence regarding submissions to SIU Press "Writing Baseball" series, 1998 (Box 2780, Folder 3)
  - "Great Pool Stories"; Great Pool Stories anthology correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2780, Folder 4)
  - "Univ N. Texas-Poetry Anthol."; Correspondence regarding the University of North Texas Press Ray Gonzalez poetry anthology, 1994-1996 (Box 2780, Folder 5)
  - "Arts & Letters Live/Texas Bound"; Correspondence regarding Texas Bound reading series, 1994-1998 (Box 2780, Folder 6)
  - "Best of Texas: 96 Rancho Loco"; Correspondence regarding the Best of Texas Writing series Rancho Loco Press, 1996 (Box 2780, Folder 7)
  - "Texas Short Fiction (III)? I?"; Correspondence regarding submissions to Texas Short Fiction III, 1996 (Box 2780, Folder 8)
  - "Go Tell It on the Mtn: Anthology"; Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2780, Folder 9)
  - "Oregon Lit. Anthol-Fiction & Poetry"; Correspondence regarding inclusion in the Oregon Literature Series, 1992-1993 (Box 2780, Folder 10)
  - "Writers Forum Anthology"; Correspondence regarding submission to Higher Elevations: A Writer's Forum Anthology, 1992-1993 (Box 2780, Folder 11)
  - "Gulf Coast Anthology"; Correspondence regarding submission to Gulf Coast Collection of Stories and Poems, 1993 (Box 2780, Folder 12)
  - "[illegible] Review Prelim List for Anthology"; Master list of stories (Box 2780, Folder 13)
  - "Rejection slips" (3 folders), 1980-2016 (Box 2780, Folder 14-16-16)
  - "Editor Letters"; Correspondence (4 folders), 1982-1996 (Box 2780, Folder 17-20)